Welcome back to another episode of
visual effects artist react.
>> Check this out.
>> Woah, that Holy cow.
>> Actually
Do you guys want to see some of the most
incredible visual effects I've ever
seen?
>> Kind of nice.
>> [screaming]
>> Except for the tiny elephant in the
room.
>> Albert Einstein once said, "The smaller
the wife, the harder the life." And that
has never been more true than in
Peacock's new series, The Miniature
Wife.
>> Look at all that that really shallow
depth of field.
>> Well, that means she is small.
>> Yeah.
>> What is this nonsense?
>> Oh, she's going to open the door and
she's tiny. Oh, no, it's a big poster.
No.
>> Is she IN A DOLLHOUSE?
>> YEAH, THAT THAT WOULD BE SCARY.
>> Like real talk, that would be scary,
absolutely.
>> [laughter]
>> There was one element in this that I
thought was a really nice touch. Look at
how when he steps in front of the
window, the light in the scene, the
miniature scene, actually dims around
the window. You see it?
>> Yeah.
>> happens at every single window. That
light that's coming in gets shadowed.
>> Interesting, yeah.
>> Go away.
>> This is fun.
He's got to feed her. If that were truly
to scale, you'd get like a water droplet
of wine that would kind of like land on
the glass and probably sit on top of it.
>> Yeah, at what point do you have to
forego glasses just to hold the bubble
of wine?
>> Yeah, legit.
>> You're like
>> Yeah, it's Bug's Life, yeah.
>> He shrinks the molecules and the atoms.
>> There you go. Look at that.
>> Maybe that's Yeah.
>> So, these are the crazy shrink the
molecules.
>> Oh, here we go. Moving shot. Look at
this.
>> This one's so interesting.
>> Wait, what? Hold up. This is
>> Fun, right?
>> Holy cow.
>> Actually
>> That's insane.
>> Wait.
>> This is I think this is the shot that
they're proudest of from a visual
effects standpoint.
>> I I can see that. What we're seeing, I
think, is real footage of a train going
around the little miniature train track,
and then the dudes in the background
there, but she is like flawlessly on top
of that train.
>> those little bumps when it goes over the
the new tracks, you see the train shift
in those like small subtle ways that how
would you do that practically? Sit on a
mechanical bull that motorized motion
control that's like perfectly bumping
like
>> No, you
just take it.
>> Such a good shot, dude. I love that
shot.
>> That's so good, but then transitioning
to the live plate there of him.
>> That was what did it for me, dude.
>> A lot of the stuff feels quote unquote
straightforward. Let's just say that.
The actress is in a set with, you know,
green behind the windows, green here and
there. Uh possibly some like real floors
we're dealing with, but it's basically
This is just compositing. It's clever
compositing where you're taking the
actress and then placing her into the
scene, adding some fake shadows and
stuff like that.
>> But how do you track her motion?
>> But on this train, that's that's totally
different cuz you can't just film this
on a sound stage, you know, you don't
get your camera on a crane now. You
can't just put a, you know, her on a
green cushion or something like that.
You actually have to track the motion of
the train and apply that to her body.
>> Do you guys want to know how they did
it? The first step in this process was
to capture the plate photography of the
train.
>> Train derail.
>> Using motion control.
>> Okay.
>> They have an arm that they're operating
in tandem with the train, capturing all
that in camera, including the rotation
all the way to the reveal of Matthew
McConaughey.
>> So there's a robot arm that they've
programmed in the camera move for. It
does the whole thing, pulling back,
going sideways, and then landing on him.
>> Yep. And then a few weeks later after
they've kind of prepared for the next
step in this process, they bring in
Elizabeth Banks, and they sit her on top
of a buck, basically like a thing of
like a mechanical bull kind of.
>> That's what I said.
>> Yeah, it is what you said. This is built
on a five-axis gimbal.
>> It's a motion-controlled
horse.
>> Yeah, so they can a seat. It's a
motion-controlled chair.
>> Literally, yeah. So, she's mounted on
this this green
buck body that is mirroring the
dimensions of the train except scaled
up, right? All of this is 1/12 scale.
So, you're multiplying the scale of the
train dimensions 12 times, sitting her
on top of that, mounting that on a
five-axis gimbal. The buck was capable
of vibrations, shifting, rotating, and
it was built on a turntable, too, that
could rotate in camera. So, the
turntable could kind of handle the
rotation, and then the camera could
compensate so that at the end of the day
both plates matched as perfectly as
possible including those little
vibrations and shifts.
>> So, basically what you're saying, half
of the motion is being done by the buck,
the other half is being done by the
robot arm. So, the buck kind of comes
forward a little bit, rotates around,
and then kind of goes away like this.
Meanwhile, the camera is moving here,
which should work as long as you get
that angle correct.
>> That's the parallax correct. Because
when you are scaling for miniature
photography, again, this was 1/12 scale,
and you were trying to match that in
true scale, you need to multiply the
height by 12, the distance by 12, and
the distance that everything is
traveling by 12. All of it needs to be
way bigger in scale, and of course, that
would be a tremendous undertaking. So,
to to limit the amount of distance that
needed to be traveled, they did a bunch
of math.
>> This is really good VFX.
>> Yeah. And there's a lot of them. There's
10 episodes of this show, and there's
over 3,000 visual effect shots.
>> As a producer myself, I love and respect
all the techniques and production tricks
that the miniature wise had to
accomplish in that show. But, I can only
imagine the level of complication of
those shots. You have to stay organized
somehow. And that's why this video is
sponsored by Odoo. If you're running any
kind of creative business, production
company, freelance operation, or even if
you're just trying to grow a side
hustle, you know how fast the admin
[music] side starts to get a little
messy. You've got projects in one place.
You got invoices somewhere else, client
notes in another app, maybe a website,
maybe a CRM, [music] maybe inventory,
maybe contracts, and suddenly half the
job is just keeping the business
organized. And that's where Odoo comes
in. Odoo is a business management
platform that brings your apps together
in one place. So, instead of juggling
disconnected tools, your work can
actually talk to [music] itself. For
example, you have a website, you're
making sales, you got to send invoices,
you have accounting, you have inventory,
project management, and e-signatures
that can all live inside the same
system. So, if a client moves through
your sales pipeline, that information
can connect directly to [music] the rest
of your operations instead of being
manually copied and pasted from app to
app. That's huge for small teams because
the more things you can [music]
centralize and automate, the less time
you spend on repetitive admin work, and
the more time you can spend actually
building the thing and being creative,
the thing that's fun, right? It's also
scalable, so you can start with what you
need now and add more [music] apps as
your business grows. The first app is
free for life, including unlimited
hosting and support, and if you want
access to all the available apps, the
plans only start at $24.90 per month.
So, if you're running a business,
managing projects, selling products, or
just trying to get your operations out
of a dozen different tabs, check out
Odoo at the link in the description or
scan the QR code on screen to check it
out. Maybe this can help you kick off
that business that you've always dreamed
about starting or help you streamline
one that you've already started
building. Thanks again to Odoo for
sponsoring. Now, I think you're really
going to like this next react clip.
>> Hidden stairs?
>> Yeah, another motion control played
there.
>> That light wrap. People love that light
wrap.
>> Yeah.
>> You know what would make this look
better? A little bit of just random like
glowing inner glow.
>> Yeah, yeah. Really eat away those edges.
>> like I would look better with some inner
glow.
>> Can we hit Sam with some inner glow real
quick?
>> Can you wrap us?
>> Edge wrap.
>> Edge [laughter] wrap.
>> Run!
>> And then how do you deal with bugs when
you're small?
>> Dude.
>> But I like this shot. I love the contact
with the window.
>> Yeah.
>> That's so fun.
>> Yeah, I like that. I like that.
>> Tippett Studios worked on this. Phil
Tippett, but they did the fly here.
>> That was a big fly, dude.
>> dude's a buff boy.
>> Like even on the on their miniature
scale, that's a big fly.
>> Good eye, dude. Yeah, cuz they did a
1/12 scale version of basically the fly
model, but in relation to how tall she
is. She's a just shy of 6 in I believe
at 1/12 scale to her original size.
>> THAT'S THE BIGGEST FLY, DUDE. That's a
1-in fly.
>> So, they they actually balloon the scale
of the fly to make it feel more
dangerous cuz at true scale at 1/12
scale, it still felt like it wasn't that
intimidating. So, they balloon that
thing. And then the actual the actual
flying model like the CG in this looks
really good to me. Overall really well
done though considering scope,
considering timeline like again 3,000
shots across 10 episodes, really fun, a
huge undertaking.
>> This is a Coca-Cola commercial from 2006
directed by Nagi Noda who's a Japanese
pop artist who passed away a couple
years after this. This is a big one-er
and a bunch of clone effects.
>> So, when you say clone effects, I mean
this could just be similarish looking
people.
>> Oh, but like the door. I mean, it's a
cool concept of doing like the
the onion peel the onion skin
effect.
>> Wouldn't it be crazy if this is all in
camera?
Woah, they did this? Oh, a blink. Did I
see a blink?
>> Yeah, this is like the most 2006 thing
I've ever seen and I love it.
>> Oh, ooh they all turned.
>> And scene. Ready?
>> for a second one. That's what it means.
IT WAS ALL IN CAMERA.
YES.
>> THAT'S THE SAME GIRL from the beginning
at the very end. So, once they film her
and they go around, she goes out and
around and then meets up there at the
end. But this is a commercial that aired
only once in Australia.
>> Why?
>> There's so much mystery around this.
>> It's a really long commercial, that's
why.
>> It's a 90-second commercial, you're
right, and it kind of only works in its
entirety.
>> That's valid.
>> At first kind of seems like some
advanced visual effects trickery going
on, whereas in reality, they just rented
out a mega church and got hundreds of
people. So, you got that house in the
background, but the walls are just like
painted on. They filled out the set.
They took out all the chairs. They
filled it with grass and dirt and kind
of made it looking like a set.
>> It's just neat seeing each frame has its
own dynamic beat to it as well.
>> Yeah. This is the sort of thing you
wouldn't be able to get away with with
modern like 4K cameras because the
detail would be way too easily seen that
oh, these are all just different people.
>> That's a super fun commercial. I don't
get it, but I like it a lot.
>> But also, this video was uploaded April
2006 on YouTube. This is a 20-year-old
video.
>> Oh, dude, the weight of time is hitting
me so hard right now. Oh my god, a
20-year-old YouTube video.
There's this movie called They Will Kill
You. Check out this very satisfying
flaming axe murder scene.
CHECK THIS OUT.
>> WOAH.
>> [screaming]
>> WOAH, WAIT. WHAT THE HECK?
>> THAT'S CRAZY.
>> First thing, make sure that all your bad
guys are flammable.
>> Doesn't this look so cool?
>> super cool. So, that that's all real
fire, isn't it?
>> [screaming]
>> Her hair is so flammable.
>> I know. That's the thing I think too.
The whole time I'm like, okay, first
off, if they're using real fire, it's
like how did she not light her hair on
fire? Cuz that looks like very flammable
hair.
>> Ready to go, yeah.
>> And she's always lifting that axe right
past her. She's swinging there. I'm
like, oh my god.
>> Would it be crazy to throw her in a
hairnet and give her like a wig that
isn't flammable? Is that a thing?
>> Yeah.
>> That would be an option.
>> You can make stuff that's not flammable.
>> The first time I watched this, I was
like, wow, obviously they're using some
real fire, but there's no way it's all
real.
>> I mean, maybe like some of those embers
coming up and stuff could be composited
and added.
>> Yeah, the embers don't look real to me.
>> I feel like sometimes it's like being
augmented with like extra sparks and
stuff.
>> There's still tons of fire video
effects, you're right. The embers, the
impacts, all that we're seeing, if you
watch it closely, you can definitely see
that is being augmented to make the
impacts feel really powerful. You throw
some embers on there, you throw an
additional fire burst to really sell
like the hit.
>> Yeah.
>> Then for your stunt performers, they are
wearing perfect clothes for fire stunts.
They're fully covered and then wrapped
up. They've got flame retardant like
jelly all over them except for the patch
where they know they're going to get
hit. So, when that torch makes contact,
boom, it lights them up. You augment it
with some sparks. You see that natural
transfer of the flame.
>> And the most important thing is you get
the illumination in the scene from the
real fire all across their back. It's
casting shadows.
>> Yeah, the the first thing I noticed that
was like making me think this was real
fire was just seeing all of the lighting
on the ground matching the flickering.
>> Like the fire would flicker at the same
rate that the reflections were
flickering.
>> And the amount of light being cast cuz
if you're if you're not doing anything
for lighting there, you can't fix that
in post. That's too much. Like full
illumination in a dark room to the level
of fire, how much fire would illuminate
an area.
>> Yeah, you can't fake that with LED
lights, either.
>> No.
>> If any of this fire is fake, this is how
you do fake fire. It looks like this.
>> They're taking you back 65 million years
to hunt the greatest predator the world
has ever seen.
>> So, this is a movie called The Sound of
Thunder. It came out in 2005. It's a
time travel movie where they go back in
time to hunt dinosaurs for fun.
>> Okay, yeah.
>> But it's also a little bit of the
butterfly effect as well.
>> You hunt the wrong dinosaur.
>> Yep.
>> They only are hunting dinosaurs that
they know are about to die. So, it
doesn't change the timeline at all.
>> Woah!
Shaky.
>> Damn, this is HOW THEY GO?
>> [laughter]
>> I'M GETTING SICK, DUDE.
>> WHY NOT MORE LIKE AERODYNAMIC?
>> [laughter]
>> THE whole story behind this is kind of
nuts. It started out as an 80 million
dollar movie in 2005. The sets are all
very extravagant. They've got big
actors. Ben Kingsley is in this movie.
>> elaborate, expensive, authentic, and a
fantasy.
>> The company went out of business and so
they didn't have any money for the
movie. And so that's why all of the
effects look like pre-vis because it
actually is.
>> Oh my god.
>> the pre-vis.
>> Or post-vis rather.
>> Woah.
So these were intended to just be the
round one animation and timing
approvals.
>> Hit him with the flashlight.
>> Come over here.
>> Over here. Come on over here.
>> It's straight out of Jurassic Park.
That's where they learned this. They had
all of these visual effects planned for
it, but then they're filming in Europe
and they had historic flooding and it
ruined half their sets. And so they
ended up having to shoot a lot more on
green screen than they initially
intended to. And then the budget dropped
from 80 million to 30 million.
>> Like by surprise?
>> Yeah. So you ended up with a much
smaller list of effects artists with
significantly less time to do all of the
effects and they have to just crank it
out.
Also get this. Their bullets are made
out of frozen nitrogen so that they
leave no trace. But little do they know
someone stepped on a butterfly.
>> No.
>> A single butterfly. Isn't that amazing?
>> This is based on Ray Bradbury's short
story.
>> Dude, if he never wrote that book, this
movie would have never got made.
>> Oh my god.
>> [laughter]
>> If you think about it.
>> Woah.
Hold on. I'm going [laughter] to need a
minute.
>> They've now messed up the timeline and
what that means is that monkeys have
evolved.
>> So monkeys are smart now.
>> So they become monkasours? I don't
understand. [laughter]
>> Monkasours?
>> What did he step on that made happen?
>> Are they bulletproof?
They're bulletproof?
>> Oh, it's a baboonasaur, dude. It's a
>> Well, they're in the presence, so they
can use real guns now, can't they?
>> Baboonasaur?
>> Baboonasaur.
>> Hey, this animation isn't half bad.
>> kind of what I was thinking. It's like
cuz I heard so much crap about this
movie, and then when I actually started
watching through it, seeing the sheer
volume of effects in here, I'm impressed
they were able to get the quality that
they did have. It's just It's really
just the city stuff that everyone's
like, "Ooh."
>> Well, you're hunters, so shoot me.
You're so close to the way Timmy's being
used. What's going on?
>> Ooh.
>> I want to hear that bass. Oh, they're
just sliding. Dude, they're
They're on like a moving walkway.
>> Yeah, look at that. Real headlights.
>> It's like the PAW Patrol, dude. That's
the reminds me of those PAW [laughter]
Patrol cars, where they're all like
They're all like
just like It's like It's the size of a
Hummer, but there's only one seat in it
and a steering [laughter] wheel.
>> They're legit the the toys for
3-year-olds.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> cars, man.
>> cars.
>> Chase is on the case.
>> How was the other night with the lovely
Miss Wallenbeck?
>> That car is huge, dude. [laughter]
Meatier than ever.
>> Wait, there's no shadows of the cars on
the ground or anything.
>> So, what hurts me about this scene isn't
the CG, it's that they're lighting this
with clearly studio lighting, and
they're trying to make a scene like it's
outside. They're just kind of walking in
place. And then a bit of an advanced
shot here, camera track.
>> God, they're really good.
>> Dude, do you see how much their feet are
sliding? Do you see those people
sliding?
Look at those people on the right
sliding.
>> OH, YES.
>> [laughter]
>> GOD.
>> THE CARS GO SKRT, AND SO DO the people.
>> car go drift?
>> And then it cuts to this.
Look at this. That looks great.
>> They might have [laughter] shot this
first.
>> Yeah, this movie has like a weird
dichotomy of very like high-level sets
and props, and then the visual effects
that just didn't get finished. They got
rushed so hard.
>> So, it's easy to laugh at these visual
effects, but like in 2002, when I saw
people making this online,
I was floored. I I was so floored by the
amount of talent that goes into making
this kind of stuff.
Maybe not quite at the theatrical level
like this, but even still even still I
was like I hope my CGI
is hopefully somewhere near this one
day.
>> Ren, thank you for bringing this. You
brightened our day, hopefully everyone's
day. Also, this is available for free on
YouTube right now.
>> Music to my ears, man. More free
content.
>> Yep. Thanks for watching everyone. See
you next week. Or will we?
>> Or yeah, if you step on that butterfly,
you won't be seeing us.
>> If you don't hit subscribe, we might not
be around next week.